It/O was/O launched/O together/O with/O the/O Lunar/ORGANIZATION Reconnaissance/O Orbiter/O -LRB-/O LRO/O -RRB-/O on/O June/DATE 18/O ,/O 2009/O ,/O as/O part/O of/O the/O shared/O Lunar/ORGANIZATION Precursor/O Robotic/O Program/O ,/O the/O first/O American/O mission/O to/O the/O Moon/LOCATION in/O over/O ten/O years/DATE ./O
LCROSS/O was/O designed/O to/O watch/O as/O the/O launch/O vehicle/O 's/O spent/O Centaur/O upper/O stage/O ,/O with/O a/O nominal/O impact/O mass/O of/O 2,305/O kg/O -LRB-/O 5,081/O lb/O -RRB-/O ,/O struck/O the/O Cabeus/O crater/O -LRB-/O 3/O -RRB-/O near/O the/O south/O pole/O of/O the/O Moon/LOCATION ./O
